Valley Women's Center Records, 1970-1977
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Valley Women's Center records
1971 - 1977
1971-1972
Valley Women's Center (Northampton, Mass.)
MS 383
5 boxes (2 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Women's center. Founded in Northampton, Massachusetts, the VWC identified with radical feminism and provided a myriad of free services to women in the community, such as legal and educational resources; pregnancy counseling; vocational counseling; and support groups. The records reveal the inner workings of a local feminist organization at the height of women's liberation movement in the early 70s. Materials include correspondence, administrative records, histories, photographs, publications, and subject files.
March 26, 1971 marked the founding of the Valley Women's Center (VWC) in Northampton, Massachusetts. It evolved from an Amherst women's liberation group consisting of 75 members to a non-profit corporation catering to the needs of women in the whole Pioneer Valley. Initially, its main purpose was to inform women about legal and educational means to improve their lives. Men were not permitted to be members of the organization. Pat Sackrey, Smith '71, started the VWC and Nancy Greenman, Smith '69, was the group coordinator.
The VWC identified itself with radical feminism, scorning the National Organization of Women (NOW) for encouraging women to obtain positions of power in a patriarchal society as opposed to dismantling the patriarchy. It also allied itself with Third World causes and political battles. In addition, VWC members were among the first to address rape as a political issue.
The VWC office was staffed by volunteers and it had an open library with archival material about the women's movement. The office was open daily and two evenings per week, offering a myriad of free services to women. For example, there was a free store on the premises where one person could donate items in exchange for someone else's donated goods. In 1971, the VWC began sponsoring welfare rights programs and vocational counseling. It also offered pregnancy counseling, its most used-service. The VWC organized classes in self-defense, auto mechanics, writing, art, women's studies and health, and sponsored lectures and discussions about feminism. The organization also facilitated support groups for women. The film co-op enabled women to create films about their own experience, as well as to come to the office to watch films about women.
In 1971, the VWC proposed to create the Women's Institute. Had it become a reality, its components would have included a group home for delinquent girls, designed to teach them independence and self-reliance; an artisan colony providing women artists "a room of their own;" and apprenticeships for women in skills programs in such traditionally gender-segregated fields as carpentry and truck driving. The Women's Institute would have supported research in women's history, in addition to developing child care services and an experimental school.
In 1973, the VWC began to face financial difficulties due to its non-profit status. The Center was chronically understaffed and the group had a difficult time coordinating child care for members who were interested in volunteering their time. Racism was also a concern since few African-American women were active in the group. The membership of lesbians, who had always been an active force in the organization, dwindled due to the later admittance of men to the working groups. These two issues caused internal conflict and declining membership.
After much thought and debate the group determined that offering free services to women did not necessarily persuade the women receiving the services to participate in the women's movement. Thus the VWC dissolved in November, 1973 and a new organization, the Valley Women's Union (VWU), was formed. The VWU occupied the same space as that of the VWC, at 200 Main Street, Northampton. The VWU was more structured, and members were required to agree to socialist/feminist political principles and to take part in political actions. The political ideal envisioned in 1974/1975 was a Marxist revolution with no couples permitted, men being bussed off to labor camps, society having universal child care, and everyone trading job duties to avoid alienation and class privilege. One example of VWU political involvement was the "women in prison" work group, formed to protest women being held in jail. This group was active in supporting the campaign to free Angela Davis. To mitigate the alienation of lesbian members, a series of talks was held about sexual orientation and heterosexual privilege. The VWU also created a "lesbian garden," a space above the main office for lesbians only. Moreover, men were excluded from general membership.
Although the Valley Women's Center faced a number of difficulties, as a result of its pioneering work a plethora of organizations were founded to provide the services that it had originally offered. The VWC was an integral component of the women's liberation movement in the Pioneer Valley.
The records of the Valley Women's Center consist of 2 linear feet and date from 1971 to 1973. There is also a small amount of Valley Women's Union material, dating from 1973 to 1976, although the bulk of VWU records are held by the University of Massachusetts at Amherst. They provide excellent documentation of how a group of local feminists organized at the grassroots level to address a wide range of problems particular to women, as well as the struggle to resolve internal conflicts and differences of opinion. The energy and optimism of the women's liberation movement in the early 1970s is almost palpable, as are the frustrations when the organization begins to encounter difficulties. The VWC's efforts to grapple with the political and economic realities of the times are also well documented. Types of material include correspondence, minutes of meetings, daily logs, photographs, publications, and project proposals.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Administration
II. Correspondence
III. Publications
IV. Projects
V. Subjects
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
The officers of the corporation began donating the records of the Valley Women's Center in 1971 and continued through 1977.
Search Terms
Valley Women's Center (Northampton, Mass.)--History--Sources; Feminism--Massachusetts--History--20th century--Sources; Feminists--Northampton (Mass.)--History--20th century--Sources; Northampton (Mass.)--History--20th century--Sources; Women--Societies and clubs--United States--History--20th century--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Related material can be found in the Valley Women's Union Records in the Special Collections and Archives, University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION 1971-1974, undated, .5 linear feet
  SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION consists of the organization's charter and by-laws, minutes of staff meetings, memoranda, and photographs. It also contains daily logs, which are of particular interest in that they document all visitors to the VWC and the activities that took place there, as well as all inquiries and requests for help and information via telephone, from the VWC's inception in 1971 to its dissolution in November 1973. The memoranda and minutes of staff meetings of both the Valley Women's Center and the Valley Women's Union illustrate the issues and difficulties that this group of women faced as they sought to define their goals and their function in the women's liberation movement. The series also contains several histories of the organization, or "progress reports," written from time to time by Valley Women's Center staff members.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1971-1974, undated, .5 linear feet
  SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE is arranged chronologically and consists primarily of letters to the VWC from the general public, and from the staff to like-minded individuals and organizations in an effort to network and to seek funding for various projects and services; there is also a small amount of VWU correspondence. This series also contains responses to a questionnaire sent out to women on the mailing list in 1972; the responses are arranged alphabetically by surname.
- SERIES III. PUBLICATIONS 1971-1977, undated, .25 linear feet
  SERIES III. PUBLICATIONS contains newsletters and brochures for both the Valley Women's Center and the Valley Women's Union. Submissions, galley proofs and published copies of The Woman's Journal, published in 1971 and 1972 and featuring the writings of local women, are also included.
- SERIES IV. PROJECTS 1971-1972, undated, .5 linear feet
  Material relating to projects and services designed to benefit women comprises SERIES IV. PROJECTS. The records of the Women's Institute, a proposed sub-organization that would have administered a residential community for women and girls at the recently abandoned Lancaster Industrial Home for Girls in Boston, may be of particular interest.
- SERIES V. SUBJECTS 1971, undated, .25 linear feet
  The final series, SUBJECTS, contains printed material relating to local, state and national political issues.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION 1971-1974, undated
  - Charter and by-laws 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - History (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda to members (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes of staff meetings 1970-73 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs 1970-71 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Public relations
    - Press releases 1971-73, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Daily logs
    - Dec 1971 - Sep 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8-17)
    - Oct 1972 - Nov 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1-11)
  - Valley Women's Union: memoranda and minutes of staff meetings Nov 1973 - Jan 1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE 1971-1974, undated
  - General 1970-74, undated (Box 3, Folder 1-12)
  - Questionnaire, A-Z 1972 (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
- SERIES III. PUBLICATIONS 1971-1977, undated
  - Newsletters and brochures
    - Valley Women's Center 1970-73, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Valley Women's Union 1974-77 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - The Woman's Journal
    - Correspondence and editorial material 1971, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Vol. 1, No. 2
      - Published copies, Fall 1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Galley proof, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Submissions, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Vol. 1, No. 3
      - Published copies, Dec 1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Galley proof, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Vol. 1, No. 4
      - Published copy, Mar 1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Submissions, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Vol. 2, No. 1: "Women Against War," Aug 1972 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous submissions undated (Box 4, Folder 12-13)
- SERIES IV. PROJECTS 1971-1972, undated
  - Auto mechanics course undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Community health clinic 1971-72 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Counseling services 1971-72 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Sexism in the schools 1972 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Women in the arts 1972 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Women in prisons 1972 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Working Conference on the Women's Movement, sponsored by the Valley Women's Union, UMass-Amherst, January 24-27, 1974
    [Original tapes closed - use copies must be made]
    - Valley Women's Union workshop (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Community Organizing workshop (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Lesbian Feminism (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Union of Third World Women workshop, [use copy available] (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Women's Institute
    - Correspondence, incorporation documents, and lists of board members 1971-72, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Press release and clippings 1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Request for sponsorship to Committee on Five College Cooperation 1971 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Notes on proposal 1972, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Proposal outlines 1972 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Proposal drafts
      - 1972 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Fragments of proposal drafts 1972 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Notes on work allocation 1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Action group minutes Sep 1971 - May 1972 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Financial information
      - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - General, 1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Group home plan 1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Lancaster Industrial Home for Girls
      - Proposal for Women's Institute to take over the facility, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Photographs, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Media programs: Notes and financial information 1972 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Orientation material 1972 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Individual and small group projects 1972 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Miscellaneous material 1971, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
- SERIES V. SUBJECTS 1971, undated
  - Anti-war (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Feminism and women's liberation (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Women's activities in the Pioneer Valley (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Forging a New Political and Cultural Identity: Socialist Feminism in the Valley Women's Union, Northampton, Massachusetts by Patric A. Whitcomb 11 May 1998 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Cassette tape, interview with Ann Ferguson, taken by Patric A. Whitcomb 21 April 1998 (Box 5)
  - Pat Sackrey (aka Patricia Lee Lewis): anecdotes1976, [2 original audio cassette tapes; 2 use copies] (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - "Confidential Report to the N.O.W. Governing Board on the Activities of the Socialist Workers Party and the Young Socialist Alliance," 1972 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - "Theory of Feminism From a Class Perspective," by Zillah Eisenstein: audiocassette1974 (Box 5, Folder 21)